[Arabic Recitation]
Bismillahir Rahmanir Rahim
we Intitiate todays programme,
withe the Qirat, Recitation
from the holy Quran
by brother Ashraf Mohammadi
Awu jubillahi minash shaitanir rajim
Bismillahir Rahmanir Rahim
[Arabic Recitation from Quran:2:255]
The translation from Surah
Al-Baqarah, Chapter 2 - verse 255.
‘I seek refuge with Allah
from saitan the accursed.
In the Name of Allah, Most
Gracious, Most Merciful.
Allah, there is no God but He,
the Living, the Self Subsisting, Eternal -
- No slumber can seize Him nor sleep.
His are all the things in
the heavens and on earth.
Who is there can intercede in His
presence except as He permits.
He knows what appears to His creatures,
as before or after, or behind Him.
Nor shall they compass aught of His
knowledge, except as He wills.
His throne does extend over
the heavens and the earth,
and He feels no fatigue in the
guarding and preserving them,
for He is the most High,
the Supreme in glory’.
In the Name of Allah, Most
Gracious, Most Merciful.
‘Say: O people of the Book
come to common terms
as between us and you.
That we worship none but Allah,
that we associate no partners with Him.
That we erect not from amongst ourselves,
Lords and patrons other than Allah.
If then they turn back,
say: Bear witness that
we at least are Muslims
bowing to the will of Allah.
Verily Allah has spoken the truth’.
(Dr. Muhammed): Respected
brothers and sisters,