Rehema salatu was-salam a disease you
know Mohamed when he was happy he was
sudden Testament kathira behind a layer
of God I mean along after Elena hikmah
Tech when Charlene are emitted and
jarred every crumb first of all I want
to thank the the hosts all of the
distinguished professors that are here
this wonderful center of knowledge which
I was made to understand that this is
the largest university in Malaysia this
is also a wonderful auditorium to be
speaking and also to see so many young
faces out here it always inspires me to
see the young people that are willing to
come out to hear a discussion or a
lecture or to participate in something
of that nature as opposed to spending
their evening watching television which
is what a lot of people tend to do these
days the the topic and I think dr. Dell
was spoke very eloquently towards the
the the purpose of the evening we we
also prepared some thoughts for an
academic audience and I I think there's
quite a few students here so we're gonna
modify what I was going to talk about a
little bit but the the basic idea of the
crisis of knowledge is that there are
many problems in the world we have
economic problems currently we have very
serious political problems one of the
problems that we have right now is in
Ukraine which in some ways is is a
deeply troubling crisis right now
because
these are the the situations that in the
past have very easily led to major
conflagrations people tend to forget
that it was the assassination of the
heir of the Habsburg Empire that ignited
World War one which led to countless
deaths that it was the German invasion
of Poland which they considered actually
to be leoben's bomb or German living
room they were reconquest
german empire that was dismantled after
World War one and people tend to forget
that World War two was actually a direct
result of World War one and the the
utter humiliation that the Germans
suffered at the hands of the the
conquering powers at the Treaty of
Versailles so these events led to over a
hundred million people being killed
during the twentieth century but if you
actually look at these problems they
were always a failure of the political
class at solving problems that were in
essence not just simply political
problems but but deeper than that and
this is part of the the the trouble that
we have is that we no longer define our
terms anymore we no longer look at these
human illnesses that we have at a deep
level we look at them at a very
superficial level and so we have
economic problems but they're addressed
at a very superficial level for instance
the recent massive crises which burn a
key member knacait who was the head of
the Federal Reserve Bank in the United
States and did his PhD on the Great
Depression recently came out admitting
that the financial crisis of 2008 was
greater than the financial crisis of
1929 October 1929 that began the Great
Depression but instead of a
seeing the problem at the roots instead
what was done was to ignore the the deep
problems of the financial structures and
institutions and to simply bail out the
criminals that perpetrated great
financial crimes against large numbers
of people not just in the United States
but around the globe and there were
people here in Malaysia that were
affected by that crises the Irish people
were made to bail out banks in in in
mainland Europe that had nothing to do
with with Ireland but their political
class accepted this one of the few
countries that actually did anything was
Iceland where they put the banksters in
jail so the and and they refused to pay
the English banks for crimes that were
committed against their population by
people that were unethical so instead of
addressing the economic problems at a
deep philosophical level which is
understanding first and foremost the
economic system that you have at its
philosophical base because any
institution in you has has a
philosophical understanding there's a
philosophy behind consumerism there's a
philosophy behind capitalism there is a
philosophy behind despotism and unless
you understand the philosophies behind
those when when the problems of those
institutions arise you can't address
them properly
because you don't understand the problem
any physician knows that etiology and
diagnosis go together you have to
understand what caused the disease
before you can treat the disease and you
cannot if you if somebody comes to you
with malaria and you treat them for
malaria and then you send them back to
the malarial swamp to simply be
reinfected again that is not treating a
person that's not treating the cause and
so looking at a deeper problem it's very
important now one of the May
problems in the crises of knowledge is
that knowledge has been defined by a
materialistic hegemonic civilization
that does not know that does not
acknowledge other forms of knowledge so
for instance in our tradition as well as
the tradition that dr. Delp was trained
in it which is the the the Catholic
tradition in our tradition our
epistemology is very different from the
epistemological assumptions of the
current dominant model around the globe
but if we don't understand the
epistemological some assumptions if we
simply go to these universities and we
imbibe what's being taught without
having the critical skills to understand
and analysis and analyze these things
then we become victims of world views
that were engendered by others that do
not share the same first principles that
we share if we don't know our first
principles if we don't know what our
methodologies are if we don't know what
the epistemology of Islam is if we don't
know how we view truth and what is truth
if we don't know these things then
they're easily that ignorant is easily
replaced by another type of ignorant
which is a compounded ignorant it's
learning things that are simply wrong
our scholars differentiated between
simple ignorance and between compounded
ignorance al-jihad America
well jihad Basile jihad Vasya is a is
the ignorance that somebody who knows
they're ignorant has and this doctor
knew people I'll pass calls it innocent
ignorant it's something that can be
remedied but compounded ignorance is an
ignorance where somebody is ignorant and
they're also ignorant of their ignorance
and this is this is a much deeper
problem and so one of the great
tragedies of of modern human beings we
have a cult film in the United States
which is called The Wizard of Oz which
every American child has to see year
after year until they're fully
indoctrinated into
the worldview of The Wizard of Oz but
one of the things about the Wizard of Oz
is there's a scarecrow who's looking for
a brain and he says if I only had a
brain with the thoughts I I'd be
thinking I could be another Lincoln if I
only had a brain
so he's looking for a brain well he
never finds the brain but at the end the
wizard gives him a piece of paper and he
says in in in in my country back home in
Kansas when somebody doesn't have a
brain we confer upon him a diploma and
and this is very often what happens in
our universities brainless people are
given pieces of paper to convince them
that they have a brain but the reality
of it is they're actually more ignorant
coming out of the university than they
were going in because when they went
into the university they had innocent
ignorant but by the time they come out
of the university they have this
compounded ignorance and this is one of
to me one of the great crimes of the
modern educational institutions that
people are deprived of a true education
they're given what they think is an
education Educare a to lead out of you
cannot teach people what they don't
already know that learning in our
tradition is remembering its tobeco it's
a recollection of something that we
already know and this is why the Quran
says what you remind make them remember
what they already knew what is it that
we already knew we knew a covenant that
we took in another dimension it was a
sacred covenant and it began with us to
be Arabic home am I not your Lord and we
replied as spirits we replied in the
affirmative
badda shahid 'no indeed you are our Lord
and we witness to this were brought into
this world and the world is a place of
remembrance it is to remember
a previous existence it is to recollect
to recall this is why we called vicaroo
law Niccolo law because we're
remembering what we already knew you
cannot remember something that you did
not know previously and this is the
highest form of knowledge in our
tradition it is to know your Lord
Hanuman who la ilaha illaAllah this is
not being taught in the modern
institutions of learning they have
completely removed God from academia
they have removed God from the social
sciences they have removed God from the
physical sciences and they have
certainly removed God from the ethical
traditions that are taught today and he
inevitably lead for anybody that has an
intellect to moral relativism based on
how they're taught so in the Muslim
world we have adopted alien worldviews
these are not the worldviews of our own
tradition they have been given to us by
people that have come to certain
conclusions about the world one of them
is that the world is purely the material
world it's a quantitative world and this
is why they may worship the quantitative
sciences / the qualitative sciences but
in the Islamic tradition while a human
being is meant to be literate in both
qualitative and quantitative aspects of
life because we are beings of meaning
but dimension we have comprehension and
extension we have quality and we have
quantity and therefore both of them are
important to have literate people but
also to have numerate people is
important and this is why the numerous
Sciences the the quantitative Sciences
are important but our tradition always
gave precedent over the qualitative
sciences and and the single most
important of all these Sciences was
language language this is what makes us
human what makes us human is that we are
articulate beings
we are beings that can communicate but
what is the secret of our communication
when we were told in the Quran in eg
inferred or the Haditha the Angels asked
Allah to geography Haman you see to see
how hysterical Dima will you put in the
earth those who sow corruption and shed
blood it's interesting that their
question involved corruption and
shedding blood which look around the
globe now how widespread these two
phenomena are corruption and bloodshed
we have corruption unfortunately but the
Muslim countries the the corruption
indices that are done in the
Scandinavian countries on a yearly basis
the Muslim countries are some of the
most corrupt they are in fact considered
to be the most corrupt countries in the
world in fact on average Nigeria is
always takes first place and Pakistan
generally comes in second but I have a
Pakistani friend who informed me that
the Pakistanis bribed the Nigerians to
take first place so this this is a big
problem this is a major problem that we
have now the other is the shedding of
blood and the so the Angels asked this
question this is stiff hem it's not at
all they're asking to understand because
they were looking at the beings that
were on earth before humans which were
the jinn and this is what the jinn did
the jinn were here before us and they
they they they they were corrupt and
they shed blood and so the human being
was put here to replace them now what's
interesting about this replacement that
the the angel said when a newness of the
no subtlety home decor nobody Sulak we
praise you and we deem you holy and
transcendent beyond any description that
this is what we do unless is called any
animal Mallett at the moon I know what
you do not know and this is important
that the word that is used is I know
what you do not know
and then the very next thing is while
Emma Adam and a smile and God taught man
Adam all of the names this this is the
secret of the human being that we have
the ability to abstract we have the
ability to see the one in the many the
only way that we can communicate is by
seeing the one in the many when we talk
when we talk about a lecture so you you
you knew that there was a lecture
tonight how do you know what a lecture
is how do you know what a lecture is if
I say there's a lecture on the crises of
knowledge how do you know what a crisis
is how do you know what knowledge is
because you have abstracted the one out
of the many there are many types of
crises but they share common qualities
and that enables us to speak
intelligently about the oneness the the
unified nature of crises it enables us
to speak about the unified nature of
knowledge we are unifiers by nature this
is what we do as human beings we are
Milwaukee dune we are constantly making
one and how do we make one we make one
through language we can only communicate
because of the oneness of language and
this is why the ultimate abstraction is
to recognize that this diverse creation
also has a source just as every crises
we can abstract the essence of a crisis
we can abstract the essence of a crises
out of all these diverse crises we can
also abstract the essence of existence
out of all this diversity and the
essence of existence is Allah subhana wa
ta'ala this is this is our lord he is
not creation he is the creator of
creation but it's through his creation
that we know him
as the crises of knowledge we have
failed to see our Lord in his creation
we have failed to see our Lord in this
extraordinary theater of manifestation
that he has given us to come to know him
in the short time that we tarry here
Muslims are a theö centric civilization
our lives are meant to revolve around
God we are becoming like other previous
civilizations a narcissistic
civilization a civilization that
revolves around me this is the the child
civilization this is the age of the
child we're living in the age of the
infant but this is a tyrannical infant
it's not because we look at children we
have in English we talk about I don't
know if you have this distinction in the
Malay language but in English we talk
about childlike and childish childlike
is a very positive quality but childish
is a very negative quality because a
child has an innocence that we all
recognize because it has yet to be
tainted by the world
it's a sinless being but the childís
nature the childish nature is the
tyrannical nature of the self this is
enough son Amata
this is the nufs this is the ego that
does not share this is the ego that sees
that it is the only thing in existence
and everything is peripheral to its own
existence this is what the child needs
to be educated out of this is the
essence of Education is to draw the true
nature the true innocence of the child
the Bharata alia of the child into
existence and this is done in our
tradition we have no word that that
corresponds to the word education there
is no word in the history of Islam that
corresponds to the English word
education we have two concepts or always
kept together tarbiyah
with talam the idea of nurturing
the idea of educating in other words you
cannot separate the nurturing process
from the process of Education and this
is why they were always they went
together the more upbeat
the more active the more on them went
together the teacher was a spiritual
mentor as well as being an intellectual
mentor you cannot separate the spirit
from the intellect because the intellect
in and of itself is a spiritual
phenomenon it is not a material
phenomenon consciousness is spiritual
the the the very the very center of the
human being this core that that Allah
calls the lube una al-bab is a
immaterial reality it is a spiritual
reality and so the the Merapi was the
the one who took you by degrees who
brought you out of yourself
and this is why madrasa in arabic means
the place of effacement it's the place
where the negative qualities are effaced
and the positive qualities are
inculcated they called the first stage
of education Talia
the emptying out of the self and the
second stage was Tahlia the adorning of
the self with those beautiful qualities
what the ancients called truth
goodness and beauty. What we call Iman
Islam and Ihsan. An Iman is our truth,
there is no god but Allah. Islam is the
way, that we behave with goodness in the
world. And Ihsan, is the profound
need for the human being to make things
beautiful and also to recognize beauty.
and this is the human
condition. But if you look at the current
world today, everywhere you look there
are two powers ruling. There is the
irascible power and concupiscent power.
There's the dog soul,
This is what Imam al-Gazzali called the
dog soul and the
Pig soul. These are the two powers that
are reigning. The people that are
consuming and not recognizing that their
consumption is killing them. And then the
people that are effecting their rage on
the world. literally going out and
with rage in the world.
The war mongers whether they're
spreading the weapons of war and we know
in our tradition that it's prohibited to
sell weapons during times of civil
strife. In fiqh, the vast majority of
ulama said it's prohibited to sell
weapons when people are fighting. Because
Islam does not encourage fighting.
It encourages ending fighting.
<font color="#54D130"Kuna or other not on it how to be how
long
Every time they raise the flames of
fire, God put those flames out. Muslims
are supposed to want to put the flames
of war out, not to ignite the flames of
war. This verse that was recited at the
beginning and it was an interesting
choice from from surat at Tawba. But
this verse that was recited to be is a
good example. You see and the Quran
says .... You
know they the disbelievers will find
harshness in these people. This is only
during actual fighting. But there are now
Muslims that believe that this is simply
the way we're supposed to behave with
non-Muslims. Whereas the the Quran tells
us ....
.... , That God doesn't prohibit
you from showing those who don't oppose
you and persecute you religiously. Right?
Until  ...
that you show righteousness towards them.
And that you actually give them a
portion of your wealth. This is what Qadi
Abu Bakar and his Ahkamul Quran says.
.... means to be just. But
he also says  ....
That you can actually help them
when they're in need. We just recently
I've been mentioning this for years but
just recently, I was glad to see
there's a Turkish filmmaker that wants
to make a film highlighting the fact and
that in the 1840s in 1847,
the great Ottoman Sultan Abdul
Majeed sent shiploads of
aid to the Irish during the Irish Famine
and and set pounds money to help them.
This was before the
idea of global charity. This was before
the idea of actually helping other
people and I would challenge anybody to
show me many examples of this in human
history where people are suffering in
one place and people in another place
find out about it and want to help them
out. This is a very modern phenomenon, The
idea of aid. But Sultan Abdul Majeed he
had an Irish doctor, who told him about
the suffering of the Irish people during
the potato famine and the
anglo-saxon people in England were not
only helping them, but in fact they
were actually happy about it because it
was removing a problem that they had.
which is the Irish problems. You don't
believe me just read a modest proposal
by Jonathan Swift to see, although
it's a sarcastic piece, it identifies the
sentiment of many English about the
Irish. So this ship was sent to Ireland
and the English were so bothered by it,
they actually prohibited from being
allowed to dock in
their Shores in Ireland. So the
English that were controlling Ireland at
the time, did not want to the aid from
Turkey to come to the Irish. And so they
had to the Ottomans went down and they
snuck it into a southern harbor. And that
city today has a plaque reminding people
of that fact, that this is
mercy and this is based on a Quranic
injunction that, human beings wherever
they are should be helped. Algeria during
the Great Famine of France, at the
beginning of the 19th century, out the
bay of Algeria sent
massive amounts of wheat from Algeria to
France to help them. Because they were
suffering even though they were their
enemies at the time. But there's
something that transcends the animosity
of politics and that is the necessity
for us to reveal our humanity, to be
...  to be people that do
beautiful acts of goodness, of kindness.
This is the essence of human
beings. The prophet (SAM)
was called a mercy to all the
world. While  ....
we only sent you as a
mercy to all the worlds. This is our
prophet, he was a mercy. In fact
you have a brilliant Afghani scholar
here and you're fortunate to have him
Dr. Kamali, who writes extensively on
.... Sharia . I had the good fortune
of having lunch with him today. But one
of the things that he says is the two
fundamental ....  of Islam are Rahma and
Huda mercy and guidance. And I would
argue that really they can be collapsed
into one because guidance in itself
is a mercy, that the reason God has given
us guidance is because he's merciful. And
the Quran begins Bismillahir Rahmanir
Rahim. It doesn't begin
Bismillah ar Rahman al Hady
It begins Bismillah ar-Rahman ar-Rahim
to emphasize using two attributes of
mercy. But that is the essence of our
Lord is mercy and the essence of His
Prophet is mercy. And so Muslims this is
the tarbiyah
Terbiyah  is inculcating mercy. It's taking
the child out of its cruelty. It's taking
it out of its selfishness into a sharing
creature, a creature that wants to serve
others instead of be served by others.
And then the ....  is the hooda. So
tarbiyah and.... name is Rahma and
huda. Its mercy and guidance. This is
the essence of our tradition. And
guidance is something that we
cannot live without.
And because we're imitative creatures we
imitate what we see. Now we have demons
teaching our children. We have demons.
if anybody came to your house and
knocked on the door and you opened it up
and they looked like Madonna or
Britney Spears or any of these people,
Russell Brand; you know these
people because we're in a global
civilization. But if any of them knocked
on your door and said, "excuse me. Do you
mind if I come inside and just entertain
your children for a few hours." which mad
person would say, oh of course ....
Even with the wonderful Malay
hospitality you wouldn't do that.
You'd say get the hell out of here and
you would slam the door on them.
who does he think he is or who does she
think you. And yet so many of us simply
turn on the television, and plop these
little children in front of this
mindless box. And and literally allow a
stranger's from a whole other
civilization, with a whole other set of
agendas to raise our children.
I was once studying the Disney Channel.
Because Disney Channel is everywhere and
it really struck me as odd that
this obsession with spreading your
message all over the world so that
Mickey Mouse which I believe is going to
be burned in hell with the other idols.
That Mickey Mouse is part of global
civilization. A mouse is not
exactly something that traditionally
we've looked up to.
It's not Mickey the lion.
People name their children after
Lions and falcons and eagles. A
mouse isn't even an orangutan.
Which is quite a stunning specimen.
As far as animals go. I mean I
could look at an orangutan all day.
They're just so amazing looking. So,
I was doing and so I looked at some
of the the cartoon, the artists that they
have and I went to their Facebook's
because I wanted to see what type of
people these were. One of them had as his
profession,
"Defiler of children". And it just struck
me as so strange that somebody who was
doing cartoons for children would
describe themselves as a Defiler of
children. A Defiler is a Corrupter, it's
somebody that makes something
dirty
that makes them unclean. So this is
a major problem that we have is that,
we're not thinking about what our young
people are growing up with. So on the one
hand we have the .... and on the
other hand we have the ..... We
have the the dog soul which is the anger;
so half of our ummah is filled with rage
and a desire for vengeance. And then the
other half is is filled with ....
with appetites. Concupiscent appetites.
spending too much money, going and
wasting your money on empty things. In
certain Muslim countries they spend 15
times more on luxury items than the
average Westerner, 15 times more a year
on luxury items than the average
Westerner. What is that? That's a sickness.
And that's because they're trapped in
their their lower self.
We haven't risen above these two souls
because we have, according to Imam
Al-Ghazali we have four faculties in our
being. Four faculties. We have the
irascible soul which is the dog soul, the
....
soul which is the pig soul, and then
we have the Faculty of Justice which is
the balancing faculty, and then the
sage soul or the rational soul. One of
the American poets he said, "🎵some say the
🎵 world will end in fire. Some say in ice 🎵
🎵 From what I've tasted of desire I hold 🎵
🎵 with those who favor fire. but if it 🎵
🎵 haven't had to perish twice, I think I 🎵
🎵 know enough of hate to say that for🎵
🎵 Destruction ice is also great and would 🎵
suffice 🎵. He's talking about these two
forces in the world of appetite
and anger. That the world we're
going to destroy ourselves out of our
rage like these revolutionaries, that
want to tear everything down, or out of
our appetites. Where we're consuming
until there's nothing left to be
consumed. And this is a crises because
the sage soul, the rational soul. And
I'm talking about rational, I'm using
this not in a sense of
formal logic. I'm talking about the true
rational soul that sees essences, that
sees first principles, that acknowledges
reality, that recognizes beauty and
harmony, that sees that behind this, is
something vast that we cannot comprehend.
We can only comprehend it in our
incomprehensible 'ti of it and this is
our Lord this is real rationality it's
irrational to believe that this popped
into existence out of nothing the
atheists are the irrational ones not the
believers they are the truly irrational
ones and and their crises of knowledge
should not be our crises of knowledge
because they no longer believe in
anything their meaning is determined by
each individual this is their meaning
and this is why they can have wealth and
fame and the end yet they take their
lives even in our suffering we don't
take our lives because we believe in our
suffering that there there is there is
something spiritual about suffering
we believe that suffering is redemptive
this is our belief it's takfeer Avenue
it is it is to remove our sins and there
will be people that have great suffering
before they died and our profits of Isum
had hasar arthur moat he experienced the
pangs of death and actually said on his
deathbed the pangs of death are intense
so even the best of creation was not
spared the pangs of death because this
is the transition from this world to the
next world
so this is important for us to keep in
mind in conclusion I would say that if
we don't seriously address the crises in
our OMA the current crises of knowledge
our OMA and recognize that metaphysics
has been lost in our OMA the seeing the
deeper causes of things that we will be
trapped in the economic causes the
political causes and fail to recognize
the deep spiritual causes that are at
the root of the human condition if we
don't address the spiritual crises which
is it's an intellectual crisis because
the intellect as I said is a spiritual
organ it's it's not a material organ
it's not a physical organ when it when
it looks at intelligible x' it's called
bathin when it looks at spiritual
realities it's called rua or silly but
these are all synonyms for the same
reality which is a spiritual reality if
we don't address this deep-seated
problem and recognize that the Faculty
of balance has been lost that we need to
restore this balance of our triune souls
that we have intellect and we have
emotions and we have appetites if these
aren't working harmoniously in the
proper order then we either perish in
fire or we perish in ice desire on the
head of a settlement